# Avereliya Chauhan

Mumbai

+91 9552515200 /9850603686

avereliya@gmail.com

## **Professional Summary**

HR professional with 18 years of multi-function work experience in India and Oman, spanning across various industries like Healthcare Marketing, Medical Research and IT Training.

Working as a General Manager - Human Resources for a preventive health checkup marketing company, reporting to Founder – Director.

#### **Areas of Expertise**

- Strategic HR Planning & Management
- Performance Management
- Employee Engagement, Relations and Welfare
- Business Operations & Administration

- Talent Management
- Compensation and Benefits
- Training and Development

## **Personality Strengths**

- High Emotional Intelligence: Clear and expressive about own emotions and capable of reading other people's feelings. Self-regulated and don't let feelings rule. Have low levels of Impulsiveness.
- Empathetic: Capable of considering someone else's perspective, able to understand needs and viewpoints of others.
- **Excellent Mentor**: Can positively influence team members and colleagues, build and nurture fulfilling professional relationships while empowering and building self-managed teams.
- Self-Motivated and Optimistic: Capable of withstanding pressure, willing to defer immediate short-term results for long-term success. Confident and like to look on the bright side of life.
- Assertive : Forthright, frank, and willing to stand up for rights without aggression.
- Multi-country Work and Social Culture Experience: Have worked at Oman for 2 years, have stayed at Singapore
  and Germany with family, have conducted company conferences at Thailand, Hong Kong and Dubai.

## **Professional Experience**

#### Indus Health Plus Pvt. Ltd. Pune, India (June 2005 – till date)

Indus is an ISO 9001:2008 certified, preventive health checkup marketing company, with delivery partners in 63 centers across 32 cities in India. Indus has catered 5 million families, with more than 0.38 million people availing checkups. Indus manages in-house IT development and e-commerce team and a full-fledged call cnetre.

In my 9+ years association, I have managed the following roles successfully.

General Manager - Human Resources (May 2011 – Oct 2014)
Head – Human Resources & Business Operations (May 2008 – Apr 2011)
In charge – Human Resources (Sept 2006 – Apr 2008)
EA to Board of Directors (Managed all corporate functions) (June 2005 – Aug 2006)

Presently handling 500 employees in PAN India in 40+ cities and 90 centres.

My key responsibilities and achievements:

- Strategic HR Planning and Management
  - Have been leading gap analysis based on strategic business goals and Competency Mapping, ensuring human resource requirements are identified and plans are made for fulfilling same.
  - Have institutionalized Career Development & Succession Management process to proactively groom potential employees for various leadership roles.
  - Have been responsible for periodic review of HR Practices & Policies
- Talent Management
  - Have been instrumental in setting management mindset for strong emphasis on retention and grooming leaders from within the organization, giving major boost in critical areas like Revenue, Customer Satisfaction, Quality and Productivity.
  - Have setup Band / Grade Matrix and led association of Talent Management with competency-based management, driving Talent Management to optimize employee and organization performance.

- o Led Job Rotation Schemes to give all-round experience to employees and control attrition.
- Responsible for overall org. level Recruitment, strategizing hiring of both, critical skills hiring and volume hiring, via various sources like campus hiring from top business schools, external consultants, NGOs etc.

#### Performance Management

- Established objective Performance Assessment / Appraisal process, ensuring simplified communication of organizational goals, well documented process, and transparency in achievement of goals and employee confidence in assessment.
- Leading initiatives to create performance based culture. Coaching Head of Departments, for KRAs
  definition keeping in view organizational objectives and, for consistent goals fulfillment in effective and
  efficient manner.

## Compensation and Benefits

- Responsible for ensuring overall Compensation and Benefits is industry competitive and employee motivation & retention oriented.
- Leader for strategic analysis in terms of external market conditions, salary surveys and internal factors to advice management for revision of Compensation and Benefits structure.
- o Ensuring legal compliance.
- Collaborating with business managers on salary determination for new hires, promotions and transfers.

#### Employee Engagement, Relations and Welfare

- Working with all levels of employees including corporate and local senior leadership to ensure alignment of daily operations with the principals of positive employee relations and engagement.
- o Guiding HR Team for matters like employee relations strategy, negotiations and grievances.
- Ownership of the Employee Opinion Survey administration, analysis and consequent improvement measurements. Providing reports of findings and propose courses of action to management.
- o Contributor to internal and external communications strategy.
- Playing key role in Women's Committee and Ethics Committee for all relevant proceedings across branches.
- o Introduced Employee Medical Benefits, Scholarship for Employee Children and Accident Policy Benefits.

#### Training and Development

- o Responsible for preparing org. level training budget jointly with directors and local senior leaders.
- Identifying training and development needs within organization through job analysis, appraisal reports and regular consultation with business managers.
- Responsible for evaluating effectiveness of trainings and provide recommendations for improvement to ensure improvement in overall employee effectiveness and performance.
- Researching new techniques and methodologies for workplace trainings and presenting it to management.

## Business Operations and Administration

- Leading ISO certification exercises.
- o Liaison with government authorities for issues related to PF, ESI, Bonus, Minimum Wage, Gratuity etc.
- Responsible for Vendor Management and Negotiations for all high cost procurements across all 6 branch offices. Final authority for renewals and payments clearance.
- Working closely with management for expansion plans and purchase / lease of required properties. Have spearheaded branch offices setup, starting from location sourcing & negotiations till operations commencement at new branch offices.
- o Heading Facility Management & Administration department.
- Liaison with external agencies for outsourced services.
- o Heading Infrastructure Management department.
- Responsible for Facility Insurance and liaison with Insurance Service Providers.
- Responsible for overall planning, monitoring and control of large events execution. Starting with initial
  management meetings for event budgeting, I spearhead decision making in terms of site selection,
  negotiations & contracts signing and then overall execution, Supply Chain & Logistics for event. Have

been successful in reducing overall conferences expense by 40%.

# AIDS Research & Control Center (ARCON) Mumbai, India (April 2002 – February 2005) + (August 1998 – July 1999) HR Executive and Executive Assistant to Director

ARCON was a collaborative organization setup between University of Texas (USA), Government of Maharashtra (India) and The Global Fund for advance research and organized study of AIDS in India.

During my 2 stints at ARCON, following were my responsibilities and achievements.

- HR and Recruitment
  - o Was responsible for definition of HR Policies & Processes and implementation.
  - o Successfully setup Talent Acquisition team for processes aligned recruitment function.
  - o Established Performance Appraisal system, keeping in view challenges of Medical Research domain.
- Administration
  - o Led Stores Management and Vendors Management function.
  - o Was responsible for Event Management of conferences.
  - Led event management of ARCON's participation in National Conference of Microbiology.
- Management
  - o Worked with Director on Research Proposals and managed Research Publications and Newsletters.
  - Was responsible for MIS Management.
  - o Gave consultancy to World Bank for its HIV / AIDS VCT program in India, in terms of preventive programs and "eForum" coordination.

# <u>Qurum Training Institute</u> <u>Muscat, Oman</u> <u>(September 1999 – July 2001)</u> Corporate Trainer for Software Trainings

Qurum Training Institute is part of a Khimji Group, which is one of the reputed business houses of Oman. Qurum provides software trainings and web development services to corporate clients and schools across Oman.

My responsibilities at Qurum comprised of,

- Imparting corporate software trainings at Oman LNG, Bahwan, Departments of Oman Ministry and Banks.
- Teaching educational softwares at schools.
- Conducting Trainer's Training and Courseware Design.
- Liaison with Oman Ministry of Education for student certification process.

## <u>Advanced School of Computer Institute</u> <u>Mumbai, India</u> (Oct. 1996 – July 1998) Lead Trainer for Software Trainings

Primary responsibilities comprised of conducting training sessions for FoxPro, teaching educational packages at schools across Mumbai, conducting Trainer's Training sessions and courseware design.

# Manipal Institute of Computer Education Mangalore, India (Aug. 1995 – Aug. 1996) Faculty for Software Trainings

Primary responsibilities were imparting COBOL, Dbase & FoxPro software training sessions, centre management and courseware design.

Qualification		
•	Bachelor of Science (BSc)	Mangalore University, India
•	Bachelor of Business Administration (BBA)	ICFAI University, India
•	Diploma in Human Resources Management (DHRM)	Welingkar Institute of Mgt. Development & Research, India
•	PGCHRM (Pursuing)	XLRI, Jamshedpur

Personal Details

Date of Birth : 31 December 1974

Gender : FemaleMarital Status : Married

Languages : English, German (Level 2), Hindi, Gujarati, Marathi, Kannada, Konkani, Tulu